Today's דף daf is ל"א Lamed Aleph and we pick up on
the מתיב רב אחא
בר הונא. Mativ Rav Achbar Huna. It's about 10 lines from the
bottom, maybe a little more on ל"א עמוד ב'. Lamed Amud Bet.
The line starts with the word מזה. Mizeh.
14 lines from the bottom. Okay, so basically we talked in the
משנה Mishnah that the לויים Levi'im once the witnesses did not come
on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so they said the wrong פרק, perek,
the wrong שירה shira when they brought the afternoon תמיד tamid and
from then on they established the edict not to accept the witnesses
from מנחה mincha time onwards so that they would know that it
would no... that if they hadn't come until then, it was not
going to be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that day because they would
not accept witnesses even if they came. Regardless, though, they refrained from
מלאכה melacha for the remainder of the day in order that people
should not treat the day next year with less weight and with
less seriousness, which is part of the whole idea of קדושה אחת,
kedusha achat, which is not our focus. Let's see. And then there
was a debate in the גמרא Gemara we just did yesterday about
whether the wrong thing they did... they said the wrong שירה, shira,
they said the שירה shira of the weekday, or is it that
they did not say any שירה shira at all because they did
not know what would happen. I just want to make a comment
before we continue, which is that with this משנה Mishnah we have
now made sure, not made sure, we have now established that the
entire topic of קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh is in every single פרק
perek of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. It started at the end of
the first פרק, perek, it went through the entire second פרק, perek,
it went... it went the first משנה mishna of the third פרק,
perek, it could have easily been the last of the second because
the third פרק perek was about actually the שופר shofar and ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah itself, but no, the first משנה mishna had to
have... had to end the קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh discussion, right, ראו
בית דין וכל ישראל. Ra'u Beit Din V'Chol Yisrael. And now in
the fourth פרק perek we have to once again get into the
קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh discussion. So I don't know what that means,
I mean my guess is that it's because this obviously was an
area that was highly contested between, you know, the פרושים Perushim and
the צדוקים Tzedukim and of course whoever controls the calendar controls the
entire, you know, observance of the... of the people, you know, the
entire liturgical calendar. It was obviously something of great importance. So I
don't think it's any... it's just by chance that every single פרק
perek of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah deals with קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh.
Yes, קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh מסכת קידוש החודש. Masechet Kiddush HaChodesh.
Well, there you go. So anyway, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מתיב רב אחא בר הונא. Mativ Rav Achbar Huna. So
רב אחא בר הונא Rav Achbar Huna asked. תמיד של ראש השנה
שחרית קרב כארחתו. Tamid shel Rosh Hashanah shacharit kariv k'orchato. So now
we're going to get to exactly what they would do. So in
the morning תמיד tamid of the, you know, 30th of אלול, Elul,
the day they were expecting to be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah but
because they was always usually on the 30th of אלול, Elul, but
nevertheless, since it had not yet... you know, witnesses would almost never
come by the time of the morning תמיד, tamid, so the morning
תמיד tamid they just established that the שיר של יום shir shel
yom they would say would be the normal שיר של יום shir
shel yom like we say in our, you know, in our סידור,
siddur, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, whatever the day of the week is. They
would not yet reflect the יום טוב yom tov identity of it
on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. On another חג chag they would by
the morning תמיד, tamid, but on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah they would
always do the day of the week by the morning תמיד. tamid.
Okay, במוסף מה הוא אומר? B'musaf mah hu omer? Now witnesses will
come and you realize it's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so you're going
to bring a מוסף. musaf. Okay, so what is the שירה shira
that you say by the מוסף musaf of ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah?
הרנינו לאלהים עוזנו הריעו לאלהי יעקב. Harninu l'Elohim uzenu hariu l'Elohei Yaakov.
Okay,
so this, you know, through the word תרועה, teruah, you know, praise
force to השם Hashem our... to the Lord of our strength, give
blasts before the God of Jacob. Okay, now that פרק perek in
תהלים... Tehillim... let's see what we have here. הרנינו לאלהים עוזנו הריעו
לאלהי יעקב שאו
זמרה ותנו תף כנור נעים עם נבל תקעו בחדש שופר בכסה ליום
חגנו כי חק לישראל הוא משפט
לאלהי
יעקב.
Harnishu l'Elohim uzenu hariu l'Elohei Yaakov s'u zimra utnu
tof kinnor na'im im nevel tik'u v'chodesh shofar
bakese l'yom hagenu ki chok l'Yisrael hu mishpat l'Elohei
Yaakov. So obviously the מזמור mizmor that is often directly associated with
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. That's what you would say in the מוסף.
musaf. במנחה מה הוא אומר? B'mincha mah hu omer? Now the מנחה
mincha again, now you realize it's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, the witnesses
came. What is the שיר של יום shir shel yom you say
at the מנחה, mincha, at מנחה? mincha? קול השם יחיל מדבר. Kol
Hashem yachil midbar.
The voice of God will cause the wilderness to tremble because that
also is a מזמור mizmor that has a lot of idea of
voices and sound and קול kol as in קול שופר. kol shofar.
So just give you a sense... קול השם על המים אל הכבוד
הרעים השם על מים רבים קול השם
בכח קול השם בהדר קול השם שבר ארזים וישבר השם את ארזי
הלבנון וירקידם כמו עגל קול השם חצב להבות אש קול השם יחיל
מדבר Kol Hashem al hamayim El Hakavod Hirim Hashem al mayim rabim
kol Hashem bakoach kol Hashem behadar kol Hashem shover arazim vayishaber Hashem
et arzei halvanon vayarkidem kmo egel kol Hashem chotzev lahavot esh kol
Hashem yachil midbar etc. קול השם יחולל אילות. Kol Hashem yecholel ayalot.
So it could be also that there's maybe a certain sense by
the way of a certain maybe even מעשה בראשית ma'aseh bereshit imagery
like the sound of God, you know, creating... all of nature to
tremble, but more significantly, it's just the idea of קול kol and
the voice of the שופר shofar לשמוע קול שופר. lishmo'a kol shofar.
Okay, so that's what you would say. רש"י Rashi says that it's
also כדי להזכיר ראש השנה זכות קול שופר של מתן תורה. k'dei
l'hazkir Rosh Hashanah zechut kol shofar shel matan torah. That maybe the
idea there of... that voice of God causing all of nature to
tremble evokes the idea of, you know, the mountain trembling and מתן
תורה. matan torah. Okay, so that's what you would say at מנחה.
mincha. ובזמן שחל ראש השנה להיות בחמישי בשבת, uvezman shechul rosh hashana
lihyot bachamishi beshabbat, שהשיר שלו הרינו לאלוהים עוזנו. shehashir shelo harninu lelohim
uzenu. How about when ראש השנה rosh hashana falls out on Thursday?
So which by the way no longer, does not happen for us.
לא אדו ראש. lo adu rosh. Okay, but anyway, but let's say
ראש השנה rosh hashana falls out on Thursday. I'm sorry, Thursday? Thursday?
I'm sorry. It doesn't fall out on Friday. Right, on Friday. I'm
sorry. So right, so if it falls out on Thursday, right, which
does happen for us. There you go, right, that's why you get
all those three-day ימים טובים yamim tovim in תשרי. tishrei. Exactly. Okay,
so when ראש השנה rosh hashana falls out on, falls out on
Thursday, so the שיר של יום shir shel yom of Thursday is
הרינו לאלוהים עוזנו, harninu lelohim uzenu, which is what you would have
said in שחרית, shacharit, because in שחרית shacharit you say the normal
day of the week שיר של יום. shir shel yom. So you
don't want to say the same שיר של יום shir shel yom
in מוסף, musaf, because that would be the, that would be the
שיר shir you would normally have as a ראש השנה rosh hashana
שיר, shir, but if you said it in שחרית, shacharit, what are
you going to say in מוסף? musaf? So ששיר שלו הרינו לאלוהים
עוזנו, sheshir shelo harninu lelohim uzenu, לא היה אומר בשחרית הרינו lo
haya omer beshacharit harninu מפני שחוזר וכופלה במוסף. mipnei shechozer vechofula bemusaf.
So rather you're going to keep מוסף musaf the way it is,
מוסף musaf stays fixed with that הרינו לאלוהים עוזנו, harninu lelohim uzenu,
that idea of תקעו בחודש שופר tikoo bachodesh shofar is always going
to be the fixed שיר shir שירה shira for מוסף. musaf. So
you're going to change the שירה shira for שחרית. shacharit. So what
are you going to say? So wait wait, הרינו, אלא בשחרית
מה הוא אומר? harninu, ela beshacharit ma hu omer? What do you
say in שחרית shacharit instead? הסירותי מסבל שכמו. hasiroti misabel shichmo. I
have removed the bonds, you know, the bonds, you know, I've removed
from him the bonds. Now, of course, the problem is that's the
exact same פרק perek as הרינו לאלוהים עוזנו. harninu lelohim uzenu. Right.
Okay. But the point is they would divide the פרק perek into
two halves. So since again, and part of that, even the part
that does not mention תקעו בחודש שופר, tikoo bachodesh shofar, but the
things that speaks about removing the bonds and עדות ביהוסף שמו בצאתו
על ארץ מצרים edut beyosef samo betzeito al eretz mitzrayim when יוסף
yosef went over the land of Egypt with freedom and went and,
you know, and was ruler of Egypt, it's understood that on ראש
השנה, rosh hashana, right, יוסף yosef was freed, if you remember that
earlier discussion in the first פרק. perek. So what you do is
you divide the פרק perek into two halves. The מוסף musaf you
keep as the fixed, which is the תקעו בחודש שופר, tikoo bachodesh
shofar, which is what you want to be having for מוסף musaf
of ראש השנה. rosh hashana. The שחרית, shacharit, which normally would be
the exact same, you say the other half of that פרק. perek.
You want it to be different, but you're going to say the
other half, you won't do a repeat, you'll say the other half.
So in the morning you say the second half, which talks about
יוסף yosef being freed, and in מוסף musaf you do the first
half, which talks about תקעו בחודש שופר. tikoo bachodesh shofar. Okay. Now,
that's all very nice if you know by שחרית shacharit that it's
ראש השנה. rosh hashana. But let's say you don't know yet by
שחרית shacharit that it's ראש השנה. rosh hashana. So by שחרית shacharit
you said, you said the normal שיר של יום shir shel yom
of Thursday. So then what are you going to do, what's going
to happen at מוסף? musaf? ואם באו עדים אחר תמיד של שחר,
veim bau edim achar tamid shel shachar, the witnesses came after שחרית,
shacharit, so for the morning you already said the Thursday שיר של
יום, shir shel yom, and you already said תקעו בחודש שופר, tikoo
bachodesh shofar, then אומר הרינו, omer harninu, so then you're going to
repeat it in מוסף. musaf. You will have it, you will do
it twice. אף על פי שחוזר וכופלה במוסף, af al pi shechozer
vechofula bemusaf, even though you're going to repeat it. Okay, so you
get the idea? So you have here, right,
שחרית shacharit you say שיר של יום, shir shel yom, the normal
שיר של יום. shir shel yom. מוסף musaf you say the הרינו,
harninu, right, which is the תקעו בחודש שופר. tikoo bachodesh shofar.
And מנחה, mincha, the תמיד של בין הערביים, tamid shel bein haarbayim,
you say קול
ה'
בכח. kol hashem bakoach. Okay. So that's what you did. Now, if
it's Thursday, then this normally becomes הרינו, harninu, right, that's the thing
of Thursday. So if you know by שחרית shacharit then it's already
ראש השנה, rosh hashana, so you're only going to do the second
half of this. You're only going to do the, you know, the
עדות ביהוסף שמו, edut beyosef samo, which is because of, because of
ביהוסף, beyosef, because that's because it's also, it's the second half, but
that you'll do the second half and here you'll do the first
half, ושלום על ישראל. veshalom al yisrael. This is relevant because of
תקעו בחודש שופר, tikoo bachodesh shofar, this is relevant because יוסף יצא
מבית האסורים. yosef yatza mibeit haasurim. But if you did not know
by the morning, so by the morning you thought it would not
yet, you didn't yet realize it was ראש השנה, rosh hashana, you're
going to say הרינו harninu and you'll repeat הרינו harninu here. Now,
one minute. Why is that relevant for us? Because we're trying to
prove whether what they did was when they didn't know. Like, this
is, remember the question is when they did not know
at מנחה mincha time, did they not say anything, or did they
say the weekday thing? Right? That was the question if you remember
in the debate in our משנה. mishna. What do you when you
didn't know? Did you not do any שיר shir or did you
say the, or did you say the weekday one? So now the
גמרא's gemara going to say let's see if we can infer it
here because here it comes to שחרית, shacharit, witnesses haven't come,
you
don't... Right, but according to your idea that at מנחה Mincha where
they didn't know they didn't say anything, so here on a Thursday
if you don't know at שחרית, Shacharit, you shouldn't be saying any
שיר של יום. Shir Shel Yom. Okay, so you see obviously when
you don't know, you say the weekday one and that's how you
can get the scenario that you wind up repeating it and saying
it twice. One minute. So it says like
this, ואי אמרת בשלמא כל היכא דמסתפקא אמרינן שיר דחול, ve-ee imarta
bishleima kol heicha de-mistapka amrino shir de-chol, if you say that when
you don't know, you say the weekday one and that's what happened
when we didn't know at מנחה Mincha time, היינו דקאמר אומר וכופלו.
hainu de-ka'mar omer ve-koflo. That's why you'll wind up saying the שיר
של יום Shir Shel Yom הנינו לאלוקים עוזנו Haneenu Leloikim Azaynu if
it was Thursday and you didn't yet know, and then by מוסף
Mussaf when it became ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you'll repeat it. ואי
אמרת לא אמר כלל, ve-ee imarta lo amar klal, but if you
say when you don't know you don't say it at all, מאי
אומר וכופלו? mai omer ve-koflo? Why would you repeat it? You shouldn't
say anything Thursday morning. So גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם דשיר
דיומא הוא. shani hatam de-shir de-yoma hu. No, that's different because here,
right, the general practice on שחרית Shacharit was to say the שיר
של יום, Shir Shel Yom, that's what we did even when we
knew it was ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? Even in a normal
day, let's say the witnesses came in and we knew it was
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, שחרית Shacharit we said the שיר של יום.
Shir Shel Yom. If it was Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday, or
שבת, Shabbos, we would always say the שיר של יום Shir Shel
Yom even when we knew it was ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The
only thing was when was Thursday ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, we didn't
want it to be a repeat. But if you don't know, it's
not so bad to say the normal שיר של יום Shir Shel
Yom because that's what we do anyway on a normal שחרית Shacharit
even when we know it's ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The issue we
were talking about was when you don't know by מנחה Mincha time.
There, right, when you know it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah we never
say the שיר של יום. Shir Shel Yom. So there, if we
don't know whether at this stage whether it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
or not, you could argue don't say anything. Why say the שיר
של יום? Shir Shel Yom? The normal שיר של יום Shir Shel
Yom is totally inappropriate here. So here maybe when we didn't know
we didn't say anything rather than saying something totally inappropriate. But here
if we don't know, fine, we'll do the normal שיר של יום,
Shir Shel Yom, it's what we normally do anyway even when we
know it's ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, yes, Charlie?
How could you know that it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in time
for the morning תמיד Tamid because it's given before sunrise
and the court wouldn't be examining witnesses that early?
Yeah, but I don't know, maybe everybody saw it the night before
and you told them to hold off on the morning תמיד Tamid
so you could finish processing it or something or maybe you accepted
the witnesses very quickly before they got to pouring the wine because
you would only say the שיר Shir by the wine. But it
is a good question. It would be very, very rare that you
would know here. And that's basically anyway the point. Here we always
say the שיר של יום. Shir Shel Yom. We basically never know
at this stage it's ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So to say we're
just going to say the normal שיר של יום Shir Shel Yom
makes sense, whereas by מנחה Mincha since you always or almost always
by then know it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and we never say
the weekday שיר של יום Shir Shel Yom when it's ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, there if we don't know maybe we'll just say nothing.
So you can't prove based on what you don't know if you
don't know here where we'll do the standard thing to tell you
what you do when you don't know here there we might do
nothing. Yes.
This was before they decided not to accept witnesses at מנחה? Mincha?
Yeah, we're trying to figure out in that pre-תקנה Takkana period what
did they do wrong that one time they did it wrong? Did
they not do anything or did they say the wrong thing? Okay,
let's just continue a little bit. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא. Baraita. רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Akiva. בראשון מה אומר? Barishon mah omer? Now we get to
sort of move beyond that precedent of exactly what their mistake was
and focus on just generally what was the שיר של יום, Shir
Shel Yom, okay? So this is the basis of our שיר של
יום. Shir Shel Yom. This is the basis right of it is
in תמיד. Tamid. Did you remember that from learning תמיד? Tamid? I
know, but okay, anyway, alright, so yes, it's a משנה Mishna in
תמיד, Tamid, let's take our ברייתא Baraita actually, there's a משנה Mishna
that's very similar. רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי עקיבא בראשון מה אומר
אומרים, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Akiva barishon mah omer omrim, what
do they say on Sunday? What did they say in the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? לה' הארץ ומלואה. Lashem ha'aretz umlo'ah. To God is
the land and its fill. על שם שקנה והקנה ושליט בעולמו al
shem shekanah vehiknah veshallit be'olamo because God created the world and והקנה
vehiknah and transferred it over to human beings, of course he didn't
transfer it over to human beings then but it was for the
purpose of giving it over, ושליט בעולמו veshallit be'olamo and ruled over
his the entire world. So לה' הארץ ומלואה. Lashem ha'aretz umlo'ah. It's
interesting the word והקנה vehiknah there because that doesn't seem relevant yet
to the theme or to what happened on the first day of
creation. בשני מה היו אומרים? Basheini mah hayu omrim? What do they
say on Monday? גדול ה' ומהולל מאד. Gadol Hashem u'mehulal me'od. God
is great and much praised. על שם שחילק מעשיו ומלך עליהם al
shem shechilek ma'asav umalach aleihem because he divided his creations meaning he
split the waters above and the waters below and he was and
he ruled over them. Now what exactly does that have to do
with
גדול ה' ומהולל מאד? Gadol Hashem u'mehulal me'od? רש"י Rashi
says because the פסוק passuk is about the end of the פסוק
passuk there is what's the end of the פסוק passuk about הר
קדשו? Har Kodsho? Hold on,
it's באלקינו הר קדשו be'elokeinu har kodsho in God's holy mountain. So
somehow the idea of God being up on a mountain and dividing
the רקיע Rakia from the land somehow evokes that idea of the
division of the רקיע Rakia and the waters above. and the waters
below that happened on Monday.
And he to rule from. Right.
Yeah, so he has a place to rule from, right,
which wasn't there before.
Exactly. So there was basically a רקיע. rakia. בשלישי היו אומרים, B'shlishi
hayu omrim, on Tuesday, which is right when the earth brings forth
the vegetation and the waters collect to make the ocean, היו אומרים,
hayu omrim, אלוקים נצב בעדת אל, Elokim nitzav b'adat E-l, God stands
amongst the congregation of God,
אשר שגילה ארץ בחכמתו והכין תבל לעדתו. asher shegila eretz b'chochmato vehichin
tevel la'adato. It rhymes a little bit here, you wonder if there
was also this somehow liturgical as well, even this description, you hear
these descriptions are a little poetic. So he revealed the land and
he prepared the dry land for his community. So that's בעדת אל,
b'adat E-l, there's a sense of he made it habitable for people
to live in, an עדה. eda. ברביעי היו אומרים, B'revi'i hayu omrim,
on Wednesday, which is the day that the luminaries were created, אל
נקמות ה', E-l nekamot Hashem, God is a God of vengeance, על
שם שברא חמה ולבנה ועתיד ליפרע מעובדיהם, al shem shebara chama ulevana
ve'atid lipara me'ovdeihem, he created the sun and the
moon and in the end he's going to
pay back those that worship them, the worshippers of the sun and
the moon and the stars and the constellations. So that's a pretty
funny thing to be associating with these things which are so much
about giving us heat and light
and translating it through the lens of
עבודה זרה avoda zara and idolatry. Exactly. Well, there is the פסוק
pasuk in דברים, Devarim, אשר חלק ה' אלקיך אותם לכל העמים אשר
תחת כל השמים. asher chalak Hashem Elokecha otam l'chol ha'amim asher tachat
kol hashamayim. Okay. בחמישי היו אומרים, B'chamishi hayu omrim, what did they
say on the fifth day, which is the birds and the
fish, הרנינו לאלהים עוזנו, harninu l'Elohim uzenu, give forth song to God
of our strength, על שם שברא עופות ודגים לשבח לשמו, al shem
shebara ofot vedagim leshabeach lishmo, because of all of the beauty of
diversity of creation that praise God's name. Rashi says we praise God's
name by seeing the diversity of nature. Again, that's a pretty weak
tie-in, that whole פסוק, pasuk, עדות ביהוסף שמו בצאתו על ארץ מצרים.
edut biYehosef samo b'tzeto al eretz Mitzrayim. What's that have to do
with
Thursday? There are so many פרקים perakim in תהלים Tehillim that talk
about praising God, and ones that more explicitly talk about praising God
because of the beauty and diversity of nature.
It's basically the praising of God specifically around moments of creation.
Yeah. So where do you see that in the שיר של יום
shir shel yom of חמישי? chamishi? למנצח על הגיתית הרנינו
לאלהים עוזנו הריעו לאלהי יעקב שאו זמרה ותנו תוף כנור נעים עם
נבל תקעו בחודש שופר בכסא ליום חגנו כי חוק לישראל הוא משפט
לאלהי יעקב. Lamnatzeach al hagittit harninu l'Elohim uzenu hari'u l'Elohei Yaakov se'u
zimra utnu tof kinnor na'im im navel tik'u vachodesh shofar bakeseh l'yom
chagenu ki chok l'Yisrael hu mishpat l'Elohei Yaakov. Where's that have to
do with creation? There are so many more פרקים perakim in תהלים
Tehillim that have to do with creation and God and the beauty,
right. Okay. בשישי היו אומרים, B'shishi hayu omrim,
on Friday they would say ה' מלך גאות לבש, Hashem malach ge'ut
lavesh, God is king, he cloaks himself from glory, על
שם שגמר מלאכתו ומלך עליהם, al shem shegamar melachto umalach aleihem, he
finished the acts of creation and he ruled over them. And there
was human beings, you could speak about God being king when there's
humans to be king over.
בשביעי היו אומרים, B'shvi'i hayu omrim, and on the seventh day, on
שבת Shabbat they would say מזמור שיר ליום השבת, mizmor shir l'yom
haShabbat, which is obvious, but even here it's given a reframing. It's
not just a normal שבת, Shabbat, but in the context here of
thinking about creation, ליום שכולו שבת, l'yom shekulo Shabbat, a day which
will all be fully שבת, Shabbat, which we'll see what that means
in a minute. It's basically going to mean this vision of the
world existing for 6,000 years and then in the 7,000th year the
world would be destroyed so it'll be a complete cessation. There will
no longer be any world anymore. Which is at the end of
the ברייתא. braita. No. ואמר רב נחמיה, V'amar Rav Nechemia, so says
Rav Nechemia back, מה ראו חכמים ma ra'u chachamim or some have
the version מה ראה רבי עקיבא ma ra'a Rabbi Akiva לחלק בין
הפרקים הללו? l'chalek bein haperakim halalu?
What makes you distinguish the שבת Shabbat explanation which you framed in
terms of the future world as opposed to the previous explanations that
you framed in terms of creation? אלא בראשון, Ela barishon, so now
we're going to say all the same thing to get to שבת.
Shabbat. בראשון שקנה והקנה ושליט בעולמו בשני שחילק מעשיו ומלך עליהם בשלישי
שגילה ארץ בחכמתו והכין תבל לעדתו ברביעי שברא חמה ולבנה ועתיד ליפרע
מעובדיהם בחמישי שברא עופות ודגים לשבח לשמו בשישי שגמר מלאכתו ומלך עליהם.
Barishon shekana vehikna v'shalit be'olamo b'sheni shechilek ma'asav umalach aleihem b'shlishi shegila
eretz b'chochmato vehichin tevel la'adato b'revi'i shebara chama ulevana ve'atid lipara me'ovdeihem
b'chamishi shebara ofot vedagim leshabeach lishmo b'shishi shegamar melachto umalach aleihem. בשביעי,
B'shvi'i, so all the first six he agrees, but on the seventh,
על שם ששבת, al shem sheshavat, the simple explanation, God rested from
creation. That's מזמור שיר ליום השבת. mizmor shir l'yom haShabbat. Why do
you have to make any חכמות chochmot that it's about the future
world? וקמיפלגי בדרב קטינא, Ukamifligi b'deRav Kattina, and
what they're debating is the position of Rav Kattina. דאמר רב קטינא,
De'amar Rav Kattina, as Rav
Kattina says, שיתא אלפי שני הוי עלמא, shita alfei shenei havei alma,
the world will exist for 6,000 years, so we're in the last
200 and change years of the world, וחד חרוב, vechad charuv, and
one year it'll be destroyed. There will be all creation will cease.
שנאמר ונשגב ה' לבדו ביום ההוא, Shene'emar venisgav Hashem levado bayom hahu,
God will be lifted up alone on that day, and a day
of God is a thousand years. So that's what Rav Kattina says.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, Abaye disagrees and he says תרי חרוב, trei
charuv, it'll be destroyed for 2,000 years. שנאמר יחיינו מיומיים, shene'emar yechayenu
miyomayim, we will be brought back to life because the idea after
this period that the world will be destroyed, then there will be
תחיית המתים. techiyat hametim. So after two days, we will be brought
back to life, and therefore it'll be 2,000 years of destruction that
there will be no world. So therefore, whether you can say מזמור
שיר ליום השבת mizmor shir leyom hashabbat refers to a the future
will be a thousand years that the world will cease is if
you hold like רב קטינא, Rav Katina, there'll only be a thousand
years. But if you hold like אביי, Abaye, it'll be 2,000 years,
then it has to be referring to the past. Again, it's funny
because why anyway, it still doesn't get to the point of why
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would be shifting the poke- focus from the
past to the future. Why shouldn't we be talking about בראשית? Bereishis?
Why should we be talking about, you know, this sort of future
time and why do you want to be singing about it? I
mean, it's one thing to sing about like, you know, when we
talk about שבת Shabbos being מעין עולם הבא, me'ein olam haba, it
doesn't mean the period when there's no human beings and no world
and everything is destroyed. We're talking about like the עולם הבא, olam
haba, so why exactly would this be something you would be praising
and singing about? I really have no idea. I should say this
whole idea of a thousand years like the thousand, you know, creation
modeling a thousand years epochs of a thousand years modeling the six
days of creation, you know, there's like a famous רמב"ן Ramban in
בראשית Bereishit where he tries to sort of work this through, you
know, for the entire history of the world. How the first thousand
years is sort of somehow is modeled after the first day of
creation and the second thousand years of world history follows things about
the second day of creation. So you can read that רמב"ן. Ramban.
It's interesting how this idea sort of gets played out. And obviously
also in terms of, you know, types of eschatological visions that, you
know, well, משיח Moshiach is coming in 200 and some odd years
or whatever, or first the world will be destroyed, then משיח Moshiach
will come.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva laughing on the on הר הבית? Har
Habayit?
Yeah, interesting, he's looking towards the fut- future destruction,
future redemption will occur
after the period of destruction. That's a very nice explanation. Okay, so
anyway, so shifting from this interesting question of what the day would
look like on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah before the witnesses would come,
we now are just getting into the regular issue of what you
would say in the שיר של יום. shir shel yom. Now that
we've done that, now we have to get to the issue of
מוסף. musaf. So let's take a look on שבת. Shabbos. במוספי דשבתא
מאי אמרי? B'musafi d'Shabta mai amri? What so that's what you would
say at the תמיד, tamid, presumably the morning and the afternoon תמיד.
tamid. What would you say in מוסף? musaf? So רב ענן- Rav
Anan I'm sorry, no, not the afternoon, the morning, we'll get to
the afternoon in a minute. That's what you say in the morning
תמיד. tamid. What would you say in the מוסף? musaf? So מאי
אמרי? mai amri? אמר רב חנן בר רבא אמר רב הזי"ו ל"ך.
Amar Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav HaZi"V La"Kh. So this is
a very nice little acronym, the glow is to you, which is
obviously the idea that there's a glow with שבת, Shabbat, but also
this is a way of breaking up האזינו Ha'azinu into six segments.
The initially six segments of six פסוקים, psukim, and then in the
end, you know, four segments of six פסוקים psukim and two segments
of eight פסוקים. psukim. So if you look, רש"י Rashi spells it
out or the תוספות Tosfos right here inserted,
האזינו, Ha'azinu, האזינו השמים ואדברה Ha'azinu hashamayim ve'adabera etc., זכור ימות עולם,
Zechar yemot olam, that's the זיין, zayin, ירכיבהו על במתי ארץ Yarkivehu
al bamotei aretz is the יוד, yud, וירא, Vayar, וירא ה' וינאץ,
Vayar Hashem vayina'atz, okay, so each of those segments is six פסוקים,
psukim, לולי כעס אויב אגור Lulei ka'as oyev agur is the למד,
lamed, and the כף chaf is כי ידין ה' עמו. Ki yadin
Hashem amo. Okay, so now it's a funny thing to be reading
on שבת Shabbat because if you remember the theme of האזינו, Ha'azinu,
it's not so cheery, right? It's about, you know, we sin and
God punishes us and God wipes us out, and he would have
totally wiped us out, but then in the end. So it's a
little bit of funny. So let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara continues. ואמר רב חנן בר רבא אמר רב כדרך שחלוקים כאן
כך חלוקים בבית הכנסת. Ve'amar Rav Chanan bar Rava amar Rav kederach
shechalukim kan kach chalukim beveit haknesset. The same way they're divided here
into these six segments for the שיר של יום shir shel yom
of מוסף, musaf, that's how they're divided in שול shul when you
read האזינו Ha'azinu as the פרשה parsha and how you divide the
עליות. aliyot. Of course there are seven עליות aliyot but we'll figure
it out.
במנחתא דשבתא מאי אמרי? Beminchata deShabta mai amri? What would they say
at the מנחה mincha meaning at the תמיד של בין הערביים tamid
shel bein ha'arbayim on שבת? Shabbos? So presumably on the normal on
a normal קרבנות korbanot on a weekday, you'd say the same thing
you said in the morning. But as we saw by ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, at least on a חג chag or whatever, you would
say a different שיר של יום shir shel yom in the afternoon.
So what would they say not so they we already know what
they said in the morning, מזמור שיר ליום השבת. mizmor shir leyom
hashabbat. מוסף Musaf they would say האזינו. Ha'azinu. What would they say
in the תמיד של בין הערביים? tamid shel bein ha'arbayim? So אמר
רבי יוחנן אז ישיר, Amar Rabbi Yochanan az yashir, אז ישיר משה
az yashir Moshe by the which is the שירת הים, shirat hayam,
ומי כמוכה, u'mi kamocha, and then מי כמוכה mi kamocha which is
the second, you know, second part of the שירת הים, shirat hayam,
ואז ישיר, ve'az yashir, and then the other אז ישיר az yashir
in the תורה Torah which is עלי באר ענו לה, ali be'er
enu lah, the שירה shira of the באר. be'er. So what you
wind up having is between מוסף musaf and מנחה, mincha, all of
the שירות shirot in the תורה Torah get said on שבת, Shabbat,
the שירה shira of האזינו Ha'azinu and the שירה shira of אז
ישיר az yashir and עלי באר ענו לה. ali be'er enu lah.
Okay, but it's still quite funny because so okay, now we a
little bit understand why you gotta say האזינו Ha'azinu if you want
to say all the שירות. shirot. But still, like, you know, מוסף
musaf which is all about like the identity of the חג, chag,
I would much rather do that, I don't know, שירת הים shirat
hayam let's say or even עלי באר ענו לה, ali be'er enu
lah, leave האזינו Ha'azinu for the afternoon, it's still pretty funny because
האזינו Ha'azinu is not the most uplifting of the of the שירות.
shirot. in the תורה. Torah.
So איבעיא להו iba'ilu they ask the question הני כולהו בחג שבתא
אמרינהו hanei kulhu bechag shabta amrinhu when you say that האזינו Ha'azinu
is divided into six segments and and these other and אז ישיר
Az Yashir and the two other two into three divisions, would you
say it on one שבת Shabbos all six segments for מוסף Musaf
and all three segments for מנחה Mincha and there'd just be like
different, you know, music for each one or breaks in the music,
in the singing? או דילמא כל שבתא ושבתא אמרי חד o dilma
kol shabta v'shabta amri chad or maybe it would be on a
cycle of six שבתות, Shabbatos, each שבת Shabbos a different segment of
האזינו Ha'azinu and a cycle of three שבתות Shabbatos a different segment
of the other שירים? shirim? I've been saying שירות, shirot, it's שירים,
shirim, right? שירים. shirim. Okay.
So תא שמע ta shema come
and hear דתניא אמר רבי יוסי detanya amar Rabi Yosi Rabbi Yosi
says by the time the first meaning מוסף Musaf has gone through
the cycle once, you've gone through one cycle of the of the
מוסף Musaf of האזינו, Ha'azinu, שניה חוזרת שתים shniya chozeret shtayim the
תמיד של בין הערבים Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim has gone through two
cycles. So clearly that means that you are doing it one of
one unit a שבת, shabbos, right? So after six weeks, you've gone
through one cycle of the מוסף Musaf and you've gone through two
cycles of the תמיד של בין הערבים. Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. So
it's not talking about that you would just the way you would
divide the music, but you do the whole thing? No, you would
actually do only one segment per שבת. Shabbat. Okay so again it's
pretty funny, that means on a particularly given שבת, Shabbat, what you
could be saying in the מוסף Musaf would
be וירא ה׳ וינאץ מכעס בניו ובנתיו ויאמר אסתירה פני מהם Vayar
Hashem vayanatz mikas banav uvnotav vayomer astira panai mehem where it's very
bizarre, right, that you're not even saying the whole האזינו, Ha'azinu, say
the whole thing at least you get a little context, you know,
it's a little bit a little more positive at the end. I
do find it very strange that you would say האזינו, Ha'azinu, that
would be what you say at מוסף Musaf and that you would
actually even just say a few פסוקים psukim which could be very
negative. Yes.
I was going to say perhaps the reason why it's six and
why even though there's seven עליות, aliyot, seventh עליה aliya is not
part of the...
Right, it's not part of the שירה, shirah, yeah, correct, correct. The
six of the שירה shirah and then the seventh is after the
שירה. shirah. That is correct. Okay, so תא שמע ta shema okay,
so now we know what you would say on שחרית, Shacharis, what
you would say at מוסף, Musaf, and what you would say for
שבת Shabbos what you would say at מנחה. Mincha. And the same
way it sort of follows the pattern here like we said by
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you would say one thing at מוסף Musaf
and then what you would say at מנחה Mincha would be different
than what you would say at what you would say there. Okay,
yes.
Quick, could you take a question about the מוסף Musaf itself?
Can I take a question? Yeah.
Sorry, it's we sort of dealt with it yesterday. What? So they're
not sure whether they give the מוסף Musaf or not.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot we said yesterday that תוספות Tosafot says that
they would do their מוסף Musaf after the מנחה Mincha when they
did not yet have the תקנה, takana, right, they would do the
מוסף Musaf after the מנחה. Mincha.
I was wondering why most 20 19 of the 21 מוסף Musaf
animals are עולות. olot. So couldn't you give the תנאי?
tnai? Yeah תוספות Tosafot suggests that possibility too. Okay. Okay, so let's
take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר Amar Rav Yehuda amar okay
אמר רב יהודה בר אידי אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Yehuda bar
Idi amar Rabi Yochanan עשר מסעות eser masaot now that we're talking
about so now we move from what they used to do in
the time of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but then of course
the shift was also that then there was a חורבן הבית Churban
Habayis and רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai switched it
and said now we can accept witnesses. So now we're going to
sort of shift gears into the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. So said
Rav so said רב אידי אמר רבי יוחנן Rav Idi amar Rabi
Yochanan עשר מסעות נסעה שכינה eser masaot nasa Shechina the 10 10
travels
the שכינה Shechina moved or departed like 10 degrees of slowly departing
from the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash at the time of the חורבן
הבית. Churban Habayis. This was based on פסוקים psukim in בית ראשון.
Bayis Rishon. וכנגדם גלתה סנהדרין מקרא uchnegdam galta Sanhedrin mikra and that
you learn from verses. וכנגדן uchnegdan and parallel to them גלתה סנהדרין
מגמרא galta Sanhedrin migmara the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was exiled from its place
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash during the period of the חורבן
churban and that we know מגמרא migmara from tradition. Let's take a
look. עשר מסעות נסעה שכינה eser masaot nasa Shechina מקראי mikra'ei we
know it from verses. מכפורת לכרוב mikaporet likruv it went from the
from being on the cover of the ארון aron to the to
the כרובים keruvim that were now the כרובים keruvim were actually molded
on the cover, but you could take it something like the space
between the wings is over the cover to be maybe on top
of the wings, but also רש״י Rashi says, you know, in the
מקדש Mikdash of שלמה Shlomo they had these huge statues of כרובים,
keruvim, you know, on the ground, so it went from over the
ארון aron to atop one of the statues of
the כרובים. keruvim. מכרוב לכרוב mikruv likruv from one of the כרובים
keruvim to another כרוב. keruv. From one כרוב keruv to the next,
but obviously this is very it's not anthropomorphized but very but very
you know talking about it in like a physical sense, but you
know that's what you get in the תורה, Torah, the sense of
God's presence, you know, appears in a cloud and there's some physical
expression of the שכינה. Shechina. And therefore this thing is moving. It's
on the move. It's in exile.
So מכרוב למפתן mikruv lemiftan from the כרוב keruv to the to
the to the threshold of the you know where the where the
עזרה azarah no the excuse me where the היכל, heichal, you know,
either goes to the אולם ulam or more likely where the אולם,
ulam, the threshold of the אולם, ulam, which is like the entrance
hall, goes into the חצר, chatzer, right?
So you know the basic sort of structure, right? You've got your...
you've
got your היכל, heichal, right? This is the building here, right?
Then you've got the אולם. ulam. All of this is roof. Okay,
this is like the entrance hall, okay, then you have the open
חצר, chatzer, right? And here's the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so first it
goes from here to, if we take רש"י, Rashi, here are these
standing כרובים. kruvim. It goes from here to here and then to
that, and then it goes to the threshold, so it's now sort
of leaving, it's sort of leaving the, you know, the היכל heichal
and it's on its way out. It goes to the threshold into
the חצר. chatzer. From
מפתן מפתן לחצר, miftan miftan l'chatzer, from the threshold into the חצר
chatzer proper. ומחצר למזבח, umichatzer l'mizbeach, and then so, so here there
are like steps, so it's on the threshold here, and then it
goes into the חצר, chatzer, and then from the חצר chatzer it
goes onto the מזבח. mizbeach. ומחצר למזבח וממזבח לגג, umichatzer l'mizbeach umimizbeach
l'gag, from the מזבח mizbeach to the roof. ומגג לחומה. umigag l'chomah.
So, there's a question here exactly the גירסא, girsa, but anyway, so
what which roof are we talking about? רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י?
Rashi? רש"י Rashi says, hold on...
sorry for
רש"י. Rashi. וממזבח לגג, מגג לחומה. umimizbeach l'gag, migag l'chomah. No רש"י.
Rashi. לגג, l'gag, what does it say? Hold on.
לגג ההיכל, l'gag haheichal, right. So רש"י Rashi says, which is a
fun thing, it sort of like jumping backwards. It goes, wait, because
the only thing that has a roof here, right, are these things
are like, you know, these are like roof. So then it's a
little bit jumping backwards. Some want to say the גירסא girsa is
that it goes to, it goes to the wall and then from
the wall to the roof of, it's a little unclear what the
roof is. The גר"א Gra has a different version. He says, anyway,
he says first it goes to the roof here and then from
the roof then it goes down. Anyway, so not exactly clear, it's
going back to the roof of the היכל, heichal, but it might
have done that before. So anyway from the מזבח mizbeach to the
roof and from the roof to the wall, the wall around the,
so anyway it went from some roof here, it went to the
wall and now from the wall now it's leaving, now it's going
to completely leave הר הבית Har Habayit all together. ומגג לחומה ומחומה
לעיר, umigag l'chomah umichomah l'ir, now it goes into all of Jerusalem.
מעיר להר, me'ir l'har,
and from the Jerusalem to the mountain, which is the mountain which
is הר הזיתים, Har Hazeitim, the mountain opposite Jerusalem. ומהר למדבר, ume'har
lamidbar, and from there goes into the wilderness, מדבר יהודה. Midbar Yehudah.
וממדבר עלתה וישבה במקומה, umimidbar altah yashvah bimkomah, and once it left
the wilderness, the שכינה Shechinah went and dwelt in its place in
the heavens and left the earth completely. שנאמר, shene'emar, אלך אשובה אל
מקומי, eilech ashuva el mekomi, I will go back to my place,
I don't belong here on earth anymore, going back up into the
divine realm. And now we're going to show how we get this
from פסוקים. pesukim. מכפורת לכרוב ומכרוב לכרוב ומכרוב למפתן, mikaporet l'cheruv umikeruv
l'cheruv umikeruv l'miftan, דכתיב, dechtiv, ונועדתי לך שם ודברתי אתך מעל הכפורת.
v'noadeti l'cha sham v'dibarti itcha me'al hakaporet.
So we know the שכינה Shechinah begins on top of on top
of the כפורת. kaporet. וכתיב, v'uchtiv, וירכב על כרוב ויעף, v'yirkav al
keruv vayauf, God rode on a on a כרוב keruv and he
flew.
Some take out that verse because that's not in the context of
the exile of the שכינה. Shechinah. וכתיב, v'uchtiv, but another verse says,
וכבוד אלהי ישראל נעלה
מעל הכרוב אשר היה עליו אל מפתן הבית, uchvod elokei yisrael naalah
me'al hakruv asher hayah alav el miftan habayit, the presence of the
God of Israel lifted up from the כרוב keruv that it was
upon to the threshold of the house. So there you see, it
had somehow, even just by that פסוק, pasuk, it usually was on
the כפורת. kaporet. But now we see it was on a כרוב
keruv and we see that it went from the כרוב keruv to
the threshold. By the way, these פסוקים pesukim are taken from all
over the place, so it's not like the פסוקים pesukim make it
clear this exact progression. This was how חז"ל Chazal wove together different
פסוקים pesukim to explain this type of a progression. Okay, וממפתן לחצר,
umimiftan l'chatzer, דכתיב, dechtiv, וימלא הבית את הענן והחצר מלאה את נגה
כבוד ה'. vayamalei habayit et he'anan v'hachatzer malah et nogah kvod Hashem.
And the house was filled with the cloud and the courtyard was
filled with the shining of the glory of God. I do want
to say something about this idea of the שכינה Shechinah and that
word of the shining because in general, right, if you think there's
a lot of times now we're reading במדבר Bamidbar where it says
וכבוד ה' נראה בענן, uchvod Hashem nirah be'anan, the glory of God
was seen in the cloud. And it makes it seem like there
is this thing called כבוד ה'. kvod Hashem. And based on פסוקים
pesukim like the one we just read, the נגה כבוד ה', nogah
kvod Hashem, the shining of the glory of God, the general way
that scholars understand that what the Torah refers to when it says
כבוד ה' kvod Hashem means some type of a shining that represents
the presence of God. And it's נראה בענן nirah be'anan because you
can't see it directly. You have to see it through a cloud,
it's too powerful to see that shining directly. So that's why it's
seen through a cloud, but it means something is there, there's some
shining. So when it talks about the שכינה Shechinah departing, presumably it
means also in its physical manifestation as well, not just in some
like, you know. And therefore the actual shining and or maybe that
was enveloped in a cloud is moving from each of these places
and slowly going into exile.
סנה, Sneh,
it's a it's a light...
Right. ...embedded in a thorn bush surrounded. Right. Right. Right. Okay, מכותל
למזבח Mekosel lamizbe'ach and from there it goes to the to the
altar, דכתיב, dichsiv, וראיתי את ה' נצב על המזבח. Varaisi es Hashem
nitzav al hamizbe'ach. God was on the altar so he's already he's
left the floor of the חצר. chatzer. וממזבח לגג, Umimizbe'ach legag, דכתיב,
dichsiv, טוב לשבת על פנת גג. tov lashevet al pinas gag. Better
it is good to sit on the like corner of the roof,
so better it's like I'm getting out of here, better to go
up to the roof. מגג לחומה, Migag lechomah, דכתיב, dichsiv, הנה ה'
נצב על חומת אנך. hinei Hashem nitzav al chomas anach.
That God was on the wall. מחומה לעיר, Michomah le'ir, דכתיב, dichsiv,
קול ה' לעיר יקרא. kol Hashem la'ir yikra. The voice of God
to the city will call out. So it's calling out to the
city but somehow it's also like in the city. Okay. ומעיר להר
Ume'ir lehar and then from Jerusalem to הר הזיתים, Har Hazeisim, דכתיב,
dichsiv, ויעל כבוד ה' מעל תוך העיר. vaya'al kevod Hashem me'al toch
ha'ir. God the presence the glory of God removed from the midst
of the city ויעמד על ההר vaya'amod al hahar and it was
on stood on the mountain אשר מקדם לעיר asher mikedem la'ir to
the east. So it's הר הזיתים. Har Hazeisim. ומהר למדבר Umehar lamidbar
and from the mountain to the wilderness, דכתיב, dichsiv, טוב שבת בארץ
מדבר. tov shevet be'eretz midbar.
Better to dwell in a land in you know in the land
of the wilderness you know rather than to dwell dwell among like
sinning people is the idea. וממדבר אל מקומה Umimidbar el mekomah and
from there it went to its place, דכתיב, dichsiv, אלך אשובה אל
מקומי. eleich ashuvah el mekomi. I will go back to my place.
So you know this is very poignant like this idea about like
you know about A, just the fact that it just brings the
powerful image of God departing and you know God leaving the earth
and what that means you know the presence of God on the
earth and now it's no longer there. And when you sort of
describe it in stages I think it makes it more powerful and
poignant than if it was just like all of a sudden. But
it's also powerful and poignant in the sense of God's you know
desire to hold on and to still hope it won't have to
be and like the slow departure and you know the hope that
it won't have to happen and that sense of God always hoping
for us to do תשובה teshuvah and not to have to leave,
which is you know the next line which the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רבי יוחנן ששה חדשים Amar Rabbi Yochanan sheishah chodashim
נתעכבה שכינה לישראל במדבר. nisakvah Shechinah leYisrael bamidbar. It waited for six
months שמא יחזרו בתשובה shema yachzeru beteshuvah
maybe we would do תשובה teshuvah and it would not have to
leave. כיון שלא חזרו Keivan shelo chazru once we did not do
תשובה teshuvah אמר amar God said, שכינה Shechinah says תיפח עצמם tipach
atzmam let their bones be blasted. שנאמר Shene'emar ועיני רשעים תכלינה ve'einei
resha'im tichlenah and the eyes of the wicked will waste away ומנוס
אבד מהם umanos avad mihem
and like escape will be will be lost from them ותקותם מפח
נפש vesikvasam mapach nafesh and their their longing will be like a
like you know a an emptying of the soul or a blasting
of the soul which means that you've longed for something and it
doesn't happen and God says to heck with you I waited six
months goodbye and I'm you know and I'm out of here. But
again that idea of waiting waiting waiting, look you know also the
תורה Torah is constantly about השכן אתם בתוך טמאתם hashochein itam besoch
tumosam
that God knows that we sin and God still has agreed to
dwell among us. And here the point is that the sin got
so much that God could not maintain that, could not maintain being
among us with the sin, but even so that desire to still
be among us and the slow slow departure hoping we'll do תשובה
teshuvah is just a very very powerful image. Yes.
These verses were not written in the right chronological...
I said that, I said, these are all over in the גמרא.
Gemara. It's not like they're in the verses. It's the rabbinic read
of weaving together the verses to tell this story. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, וכנגדן גלתה סנהדרין
מגמרא ukenegdan galta Sanhedrin migemara and similarly at the time of the
חורבן churban the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went in exile and that we know
from tradition. מלשכת הגזית לחנות, Milishkas hagazis lechanus, they went from the
לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagazis which was a a chamber that they had
you know in the עזרה azarah
you know in the courtyard and they went from there to the
חנות chanus
the stores. Anybody knows the you know in Jerusalem you know they
have the Cardo you know they show you the stores that they
had that were lining at the bottom of הר הבית. Har Habayis.
So that's where they moved. They moved to the bottom of הר
הבית, Har Habayis, they took up a storefront there. Okay.
ומחנות לירושלים Umichanus l'Yerushalayim and from there they went they moved into
more central Jerusalem. ומירושלים ליבנה Um'Yerushalayim leYavneh and from Jerusalem they went
to יבנה Yavneh after the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis. That was the
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai story.
ומיבנה לאושא UmiYavneh leUsha then they went from יבנה Yavneh they went
to אושא. Usha. Why did they leave? So if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says כשהיה הנשיא דר בו כיון שהיתה סנהדרין
עמו. keshehayah hanasi dar bo keivan shehayisah Sanhedrin imo. The סנהדרין Sanhedrin
would follow the נשיא, Nasi, so when the נשיא Nasi decided to
move to אושא Usha the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went with him. ומאושא ליבנה
UmiUsha leYavneh and then they went back to
יבנה Yavneh and ומיבנה לאושא UmiYavneh leUsha and then back to אושא,
Usha, so the נשיא Nasi kept on moving back and forth, whether
it was Rabban Gamliel and then his son Rabbi Shimon. So the
so the סנהדרין Sanhedrin moved back and forth. By the way, using
the phrase exiled doesn't work so well here, right? 'Cause it's not
like a sense
of... Once you're in this stage, ומאושא לשפרעם u-me-Osha l'Shefaram which was
the next place that the house of the נשיא Nasi was, ומשפרעם
לבית שערים, u-mi-Shefaram l'Beit Shearim, right? We know בית שערים, Beit Shearim,
right? They've done these excavations in בית שערים Beit Shearim that they
have about, you know, the נשיא's Nasi house. Right? Isn't that where
they have those extensive excavations in בית שערים? Beit Shearim?
You see the sarcophagi? Right, exactly.
Okay, ומבית שערים לציפורי u-mi-Beit Shearim l'Tzippori and then they went to
ציפורי Tzippori ומציפורי לטבריה, u-mi-Tzippori l'Tverya, all of these were where the
נשיא's Nasi house moved and the סנהדרין Sanhedrin would move with it.
וטבריה עמוקה מכולן, v'Tverya amuka mikulan, and טבריה Tverya is lower than
them all in terms of like just physical depth, שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
right? It's below sea level. ושחותם מארץ תדברי, v'shachotam me-eretz tedaberi, and
you have been brought low and you will speak from the land.
Now that maybe is to help fit it into the exile imagery,
you know, that at the end of the process they're very, very
low, because otherwise after you've left ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what exile is it?
It's moving around, but is it like more exile than before? Anyway,
that's but still the imagery is obviously they're no longer in that
fixed established place, it's constantly, you know, moving and in transition. Now
I want to say something about this. When did this happen? So
obviously this happened in the time of the בית שני. Bayit Sheini.
It's all about where רבי Rebbe moved and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the house of the נשיא Nasi
and so on. What? פוסט בית שני. Post Bayit Sheini. Right. But,
you know, as before the בית שני Bayit Sheini was destroyed they
moved out of the לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit to the חנות Chanut
into ירושלים Yerushalayim and then after it was destroyed they left from
ירושלים Yerushalayim to יבנה. Yavne. So it's interesting for a moment to
consider the parallel, that the sense of exile that occurred in בית
ראשון Bayit Rishon was an exile of שכינה. Shechina. The exile that
occurred in בית שני Bayit Sheini was an exile of the סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, you know, and does that reflect the idea that, you know,
like in the בית ראשון, Bayit Rishon, you know, the sense more
was like, you know, the sin in the בית ראשון, Bayit Rishon,
like we say עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות, gilluy arayot, שפיכות
דמים, shefichat damim, but the sense much more was that it was
about religious sin. Right? Even though שפיכות דמים shefichat damim is obviously
also a crime against the person, but the sense much more was
primarily, really, if you read the פסוקים, pesukim, it's a lot about
עבודה זרה avodah zarah and it's a lot about religious sin and
there it's like the שכינה Shechina is departing. Whereas בית שני, Bayit
Sheini, right, it was about שנאת חינם, sinat chinam, but what it
really means, I think the way חז"ל Chazal thought about what it
really means is the amount of infighting, the lack of leadership, right,
the lack of, you know, the whole famous stories in גיטין Gittin
about, you know, about I'll make a little nick in the lip
and then the rabbis weren't willing to sort of do the right
thing and take the right leadership, or the קמצא ובר קמצא Kamtza
Bar Kamtza stories. Right? Anyway, it's all about a failure of leadership
and a failure of, you know, the divisions of the people. So
to think about that is not the exile of the שכינה Shechina
but it's the exile of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, you know, about the
religious leadership and how that is sort of the one that is
in exile and is departing. I think this is a powerful sort
of parallel that is going on there.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי אליעזר אומר שש גלויות.
Rabbi Eliezer omer sheish galuyot. It wasn't ten, it was six for
the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. שנאמר כי השח she-ne'emar ki heishach or יושבי מרום,
yoshvei marom,
because brought low is the one that dwelt on high. Maybe השח,
heishach, השח. heshach. Anyway, the one who dwelt on high, קריה נשגבה,
kiryah nisgavah, the elevated city, ישפילנה, yashpilena, it will be brought down.
ישפילה עד ארץ, yashpila ad aretz, brought down to the land. יגיענה
עד עפר, yagi'ena ad afar, will be brought to the dust. Anyway,
so if you count the various verbs or phrases there, you get
six, not ten. אמר רבי יוחנן ומשם עתידין ליגאל, Amar Rabbi Yochanan
u-misham atidin l'iga-el, from there they will be redeemed, שנאמר התנערי מעפר
קומי
שבי, she-ne'emar hitna-ari mei-afar kumi shvi, bestir yourself, get up from the
dust, return and therefore we will return from that exile.
So again very interesting, you know, because also the sense again about
the parallel, the שכינה Shechina eventually goes up to heaven. What eventually
happens to the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? Right? Does it like disband? I mean,
in a way it does. The idea of a central סנהדרין Sanhedrin
does disband and then it becomes no longer centralized. So anyway, but
I do think that as I said there is this parallel about
the God leaving or the sense also of the failure of leadership
which is the second בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, so that was
a very interesting end of that. Yes?
Isn't there this period of six months that the Jews are free
before they leave Egypt? They're no longer slaves? Right. I was just
thinking of this six here. Oh, that's interesting.
Six months. Right. So I do want to say where it got
six months. So that's a good question. The מהרש"א Maharsha says the
six months is because there were six months from עשרה בטבת Asarah
B'Tevet till the ninth of תמוז Tammuz and in the בית ראשון
Bayit Rishon actually the, you know, the ninth of תמוז Tammuz was
the date in which the city was breached. So it actually was
exactly six months from the time that the siege was laid, although
I think they would were they the same year? I didn't think
it was the same year. It is the same year?
Artscroll says it was actually eighteen months.
A year and six months.
Oh, so they're saying they just use six months.
Ah, yes.
So the מהרש"א Maharsha point out from עשרה בטבת Asarah B'Tevet till
the ninth of תמוז Tammuz is six months, but it was a
year and six months. All right, anyway. That’s an interesting point also
that sense of gradual and we had sort of a gradual process
of redemption as well with the idea of six months. That’s a
very nice parallel. Okay, so as I said before we get back
to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you know, we’re here now with the
context of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, but we
are now focusing two משניות mishnayot of this on once again the
topic of קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. So let's take a look at
this one. אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha,
ועוד זאת התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. v'od zot hitkin Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai made the
following תקנה, takana, שאפילו ראש בית דין בכל מקום, she'afilu rosh beit
din bechol makom, even if the ראש בית דין rosh beit din
was in any place, שלא יהיו עדים הולכים אלא למקום הועד, shelo
yehu eidim holchim ela lemakom hava'ad, that the witnesses would not have
to find out where the ראש בית דין rosh beit din was
even though you normally needed the ראש בית דין rosh beit din
to do קידוש החודש, Kiddush HaChodesh, but you wanted the witnesses to
always go to one fixed place. You didn't want them to have
to always say, oh, he's not here today, everybody's got to move
somewhere else. You know, like the same way they wanted to make
sure there would always be a nice meal for them if they
came on שבת Shabbat and they'd always make them feel like they
were doing something useful. You don't, you want them always to go
to a fixed place. So that was his תקנה. takana. You don't
have to start running after the ראש בית דין. rosh beit din.
By the way, besides the obvious practical benefits of this, I think
it ties into something we discussed on שבת Shabbat about whether it
was יבנה, Yavne, was it כל בית דין? kol beit din? That
the shift from מקדש Mikdash to תורה Torah also brought with it
a decentralization. So here too, the idea obviously there's a practical element,
but the fact that you're willing to be מוחל mochel on the
ראש בית דין rosh beit din and to allow the בית דין
beit din to function without the head, you know, also is a
move in a sort of a non-hierarchical
decentralization type of a way. So I think these are all very
important in terms of that shift from מקדש Mikdash to תורה. Torah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ההיא איתתא, hahi itta,
there's a certain woman דאזמנוה לדינא, de'azmuna ledina, that she got a
subpoena or whatever, not a subpoena, but she was sort of made
to you know, whatever it is, a הזמנה hazmana we would say,
to come to court. She was actually a borrower and the creditor
was suing her and demanding that she come to court. That is
a subpoena? Yeah, it's a court, it's a summons, a summons. All
right.
Subpoena is to testify, right. Okay, thank you. It's a summons. She
got a summons קמיה דאמימר בנהרדעא kamei d'Amemar b'Nehardea to appear before
אמימר Amemar in נהרדעא. Nehardea. אזל אמימר למחוזא, azal Amemar l'Mechuza, but
it happened to be that that day אמימר Amemar was in מחוזא.
Mechuza. ולא אזלה בתריה, v'lo azla batrei, she refused to schlep all
the way to מחוזא. Mechuza. So כתבו פתיחא עלה, katvu pticha alaha,
so they wrote a like a חרם cherem on her, like a
you know, like a document that she's in what would we call
it now, in a contempt of court. Okay, so this happens nowadays
as well, you know, they write like a שמתא, shamta, like they
say somebody's in contempt of the בית דין. beit din. אמר ליה
רב אשי לאמימר, amar lei Rav Ashi l'Amemar, so רב אשי Rav
Ashi said to אמימר, Amemar, how could you do this to her?
והתנן, v'hatnan, our משנה mishna says שאפילו ראש בית דין בכל מקום
שלא יהיו עדים הולכים אלא למקום הועד. she'afilu rosh beit din bechol
makom shelo yehu eidim holchim ela lemakom hava'ad. So obviously it's not
the same as the עדות החודש eidus hachodesh but it's the same
logical point. You know, people shouldn't have to schlep after where the
chief judge is, they should just go to the fixed location of
the court, and if you're not there somebody else will deal with
the case. So it seems like a very reasonable argument. אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said back to him,
הני מילי hani mili in עדות החודש, eidus hachodesh, because if you
make them say, oh you all came but he's not here, next
month they're not going to bother coming. And that's the same idea
we had, you know, earlier about the סעודה seuda and about let,
you know, all those other things that they did for them. But
הכא hacha here, עבד לוה לאיש מלוה, abda lova l'ish malva,
the borrower is a slave to the creditor, meaning, you know, you
borrowed money, he has the right to schlep you around in order
to get his money back. Now you often wonder, I mean let's
say she's claiming she didn't borrow money, you know, let's say that's
what's being contended. But anyway, but here the point is we don't
have to worry about what the larger consequence will be because, you
know, people are entitled, especially if you realize that they didn't charge
interest, so lending money was all like a חסד, chessed, you know,
essentially that we would have the system would be, you know, tipped
in favor of the creditor makes sense. Of course the question is
as I said what happens if it's not clear if that's exactly
what's being contended.
It's strange it's a woman, why would it have to be a
woman?
I don't know. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אין כהנים רשאים לעלות בסנדליהם
לדוכן. ein Kohanim rasha'im la'alot besandaleichem laduchan.
The כהנים Kohanim could not go up this is in the בית
כנסת, beit knesset, not in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. In the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash the כהנים Kohanim would be barefoot. In the
בית כנסת beit knesset they could not go up to the דוכן
duchan to do ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim wearing their shoes. זו אחת
מתשע תקנות שהתקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. zo achat mitisha takanot shehitkin
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. This is one of the nine תקנות takanot
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai made. What or nine,
excuse me. Why did he do this? So the גמרא Gemara there
explains that if a כהן kohen has his shoes and he bends
down to tie his shoelace, so then people will see that he's
not participating in the ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, they won't see him,
you know, they'll see he'll be crouched down and they'll think, oh
maybe he's פסול, pasul, other types of concerns. It's a pretty funny
תקנה, takana, you know, of all the big תקנות takanot that this
type of a thing, you know, seems to be a little bit
minor in that context. But anyway, that was one of his nine
תקנות. takanot. So now we're going to discuss what were his
תקנות. takanot. שיתא דהאי פירקא, shisha d'ha pirka, six that we mentioned
in this פירקא. pirka. Which are the ones we mentioned in this
פירקא? pirka? So,
so, this one, excuse me, and the... right, and the... five in
the משנה, Mishna, which were blowing שופר, Shofar, לולב, Lulav, you know,
blowing שופר Shofar in יבנה, Yavne, לולב Lulav the seven days, not
eating the whole day of the sixteenth, new grain,
accepting the witnesses, accepting the witnesses after מנחה Mincha time on ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The witnesses would always go where
the בית דין Beis Din was regardless of where the head of
the בית דין Beis Din was. And this one that we just
mentioned,
which is about the time of the shoelace. It's not really דהכא,
de-hacha, it really isn't סוטה, Sota, but okay, we mentioned it here.
Those six. Now, by the way, and I'll repeat the point that
I said yesterday: if you think about it, almost all of them
are not really about being like sort of holding onto the memory
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but shifting us away from the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Like all the things that we said: now
יבנה Yavne is the center, now you no longer have to have
the תקנה takana about not accepting witnesses, we live in a different
reality, there's even a different reality about the עומר, Omer, but like
it's all about the new reality that we are living in and
shifting the focus away from מקדש Mikdash and embracing the new תורה-centered
Torah and בית-centered Beis reality. This one about the
about the ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim, I don't know how that really
exactly fits into the scheme. But anyway, that is six.
I think it plays into your overarching theory. In other words, here
he's making a תקנה takana that rules over how the protocol of
כהנים Kohanim outside of the מקדש Mikdash in a decentralized context.
So you mean like the Rabbis are telling the כהנים Kohanim what
to do, so it's emphasizing Rabbinic authority over Kohanic practice
over their ritual.
That's interesting. That's interesting. Wow, that's an interesting thought.
Okay. Okay. דחדא דפירקא קמא, de-chada de-pirka kama, one of the first
פרק. Perek. What was the one in the first פרק? Perek? So
the one in the first פרק Perek was that they would all
the witnesses that would come to testify after חורבן הבית Churban Habayis
would only violate שבת Shabbos for ניסן Nisan and תשרי. Tishrei. Another
perfect example of how things are different after חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis.
Right? Now we don't do it for every month, we only do
it for the month that really matter for the calendar, that the
witnesses violate שבת Shabbos only for ניסן Nisan and תשרי. Tishrei. Again,
embracing the post מקדש Mikdash reality. Okay, that gets us to seven.
ואידך, ve-idach, and the other two are really debated. דתניא, de-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa: גר שנתגייר בזמן הזה, ger shenisgayer b'zman
hazeh, if somebody converts nowadays, so the הלכה Halacha is that a
convert would normally bring a bird sacrifice as part of his conversion
process, which obviously we don't do and we say בדיעבד b'di'eved is
necessary nowadays, but it would normally be part of his conversion process.
So what would be the הלכה? Halacha? צריך שיפריש רובע לקינו. tzarich
sheyafrish rova l'kino. He has to set aside money for his bird
sacrifices even nowadays so that when there is a בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, he'll be able to bring those sacrifices. אמר רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar said, כבר נמנו עליו רבי יוחנן וביטלה kvar nimnu alav
Rabbi Yochanan u'vitlah מפני התקלה. mipnei hatakala. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan already,
you know, already voided that because of the תקלה. takala. What's the
תקלה? takala? You have money in your house that's sanctified for a
sacrifice, you might come to misuse it. Now again, besides the הקדש
Hekdesh misuse problem, again, a perfect example of not turning backwards to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And it's even more powerful in the
context of a גר. ger. Imagine you're a גר ger and we
tell you, you know, your process didn't really finish, technically you're a
גר ger but it didn't really finish, so set aside the money
so when there's a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you can finish your
process. So the entire time this person is thinking I'm not fully
a גר ger yet because I haven't finished my process, right? So,
you know, and it's just holding on to this fact that I
still have to bring a קרבן. korban. So he said forget about
it, don't set aside the money, forget about the fact that you
need to bring a קרבן. korban. So again, very powerful in terms
of looking forward rather than looking back.
Who said that about רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan?
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Okay, so that gets
us to eight. I'm sorry, so that was debated. So we had
six in this פרק, Perek, one in the previous one which was
about
the witnesses coming only on ניסן Nisan and תשרי Tishrei is seven,
eight is about the גר, ger, and nine is a debate. ואידך,
ve-idach, the final one is פלוגתא דרב פפא ורב נחמן בר יצחק.
pulkusa de-Rav Pappa ve-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa
amar, you know, we're going to have to end here. So we
will finish with this and find out what number nine is tomorrow.